

Nicola Balkind

Email: <u>nicola.balkind@gmail.com</u>
Website: <u>nicolabalkind.com</u>

Phone: 559 231 0547

Hi, I'm Nicola. I build community through content.

I have a life-long passion for digital media and books, and over a decade of professional experience as a writer, producer, and community manager. I'm an organised, professional and independent worker who is comfortable working across distributed teams and a variety of projects.

I have worked within tech companies, digital marketing agencies, and as a freelancer representing companies and charities of all sizes. I've also edited editorial content like websites, magazines, and a book. I love developing strategies and processes while maintaining a commitment to attention to detail. Right now, I'm looking for a new challenge. I love a steep learning curve and projects I can get my teeth into.

EXPERIENCE

Community & Marketing Manager, Yelp: November 2016 - Present

- Growing a vibrant Yelp community in Fresno, online and offline.
- Managing multiple simultaneous projects across marketing, content and events.
- Planning and hosting multiple monthly events that connect community members with great local businesses.
- Writing weekly newsletters highlighting local businesses, events, and campaigns.
- Forging partnerships with impactful local and national organizations.
- Curating content for the Local Yelp newsletter.
- A variety of onsite tasks to keep Yelpers engaged, encourage high value content and build a sense of community.
- Working with business owners to optimize their marketing strategies.
- Daily social media content creation and executing local and national campaigns.
- Forging partnerships with local media, like Fresno Bee and The Business Journal.
- Member of the Blog Committee: SEO optimization, scheduling, writing and editing.
- Mentoring new recruits.

Content & Community Strategist: May 2010 - January 2021

For over a decade, I provided Project and Content Management services across the technology and arts industries and third sector. I have extensive experience in managing projects end-to-end: strategy, pitching, managing scope, and implementing systems and processes. I've worked with and managed internal teams as well as individual and teams of freelancers.

Services and duties include:

- Communication strategies to connect with web audiences, improve SEO, build online communities, and enable user-generated content creation. Also influencer outreach.
- Content strategy (including content audits, style guides, editorial calendars), copywriting, and community management. Trained, consulted and coached independent clients and agencies in social media and content marketing.
- Experience in copy-editing and proofreading. Completed two SfEP training courses in copy-editing training.
- Experience with analytics tools, a range of CMS, and social media scheduling software.
- Examples of my work and client list are available on my website.

Freelance Writer: June 2008 – 2018

- Author of <u>Fan Phenomena</u>: <u>The Hunger Games</u> and Editor of <u>World Film Locations</u>: <u>Glasgow</u>, published by Intellect Books (UK) and University of Chicago Press (USA).
- Broadcast film critic for BBC Radio.
- Contributor to international print and online publications, e.g. Big Issue Magazine and The List Magazine.

Web Editor, Edinburgh International Film Festival: Festivals 2010 - 2014

- Head of online communications: content strategy and community management.
- Editing all editorial content.
- Improved web traffic and grew community significantly, averaging 94% year-on-year.

Web Editor, Mint Digital: August 2010 - May 2011

- Implemented an editorial strategy, sourced and produced daily blog content for Quotables – a quotation sharing website funded by Channel 4.
- Community building and management including social media outreach.
- SEO projects for Channel 4 websites.
- Content audits for clients including the Christopher & Dana Reeve Foundation.

EDUCATION

University of Glasgow: 2011 – Master of Letters in Journalism with Merit University of Stirling: 2009 – B.A. (Hons) Film and Media Studies: First Class – Speakeasy Award for Best Dissertation

University of California, Santa Barbara: 2007-08 - EAP Study Abroad Candidate